<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-02-28T16:54:57+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">ChinaComx</title><subtitle>Comics Culture in the People&apos;s Republic of China</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Closing Event of a Lianhuanha Exhibition at the CATS Library with ChinaComx</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/10/10/FinissageHD.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Closing Event of a Lianhuanha Exhibition at the CATS Library with ChinaComx" /><published>2024-10-10T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-10-10T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/10/10/FinissageHD</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/10/10/FinissageHD.html"><![CDATA[<p>On 15 October 2024 the <a href="https://www.cats.uni-heidelberg.de/library/">CATS Library</a> would like to cordially invite you to the finissage of our exhibition <a href="https://www.cats.uni-heidelberg.de/bibliothek/ausstellungen/comics.html">“Comics from China: Entertainment – Realities – Propaganda?”</a>!</p>

<p>The finissage offers a last opportunity to view the exhibition, after which Lena Henningsen and Damian Mandzunowski from the ERC project “ChinaComx”, newly established at CATS, will give a keynote speech on the roles of heroes and villains in comics of the Mao era.</p>

<p>In addition, three wonderful animated short films by young Chinese artists will round off the programme. Of course, a small buffet will also be provided for your physical well-being!</p>

<p>Program:</p>
<ul>
  <li>18:30     Welcome and exhibition tour, Foyer, CATS Library</li>
  <li>19:00     Keynote: “Into the Maoverse: Heroes and Villains in Chinese Comics,” Lena Henningsen &amp; Damian Mandzunowski (ERC-ChinaComx), CATS Auditorium (R.010.01.05)</li>
  <li>19:45     Film screening: Animated shorts from the Nanjing University of the Arts 南京艺术学院:
    <ul>
      <li>当我再次走进厨房 (Now I’m in the Kitchen), dir.: Yana Pan 潘亭钰, 2022</li>
      <li>每天朝山顶推一秒的石头 (Being Sisyphus for One Second a Day), dir.: Peixuan Cheng 成佩轩, 2021</li>
      <li>雾上清晨 (Beyond the Fog), dir.: Xue Feng 薛峰, 2021</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>End of the event around 20:30.</li>
</ul>

<p><em>Creating the exhibition was part of a seminar of the Institute of East Asian Art History; for the names of the participating students please refer to the <a href="https://www.cats.uni-heidelberg.de/bibliothek/ausstellungen/comics.html">exhibition’s webpage</a>.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On 15 October 2024 the CATS Library would like to cordially invite you to the finissage of our exhibition “Comics from China: Entertainment – Realities – Propaganda?”!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/FinissageHD.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/FinissageHD.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Lena Henningsen to Deliver a Talk at Edinburgh on Lu Xun in Lianhuanhua on 9 October</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/09/27/LenaEdinburgh.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lena Henningsen to Deliver a Talk at Edinburgh on Lu Xun in Lianhuanhua on 9 October" /><published>2024-09-27T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-09-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/09/27/LenaEdinburgh</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/09/27/LenaEdinburgh.html"><![CDATA[<p>On 9 October 2024 at 11:00 - 12:30, ChinaComx PI Lena Henningsen <a href="https://www.sps.ed.ac.uk/news-events/event/eyebrows-moustaches-and-revolutionary-spirit">will deliver a talk</a> titled “Of Eyebrows, Moustaches and Revolutionary Spirit” as part of the <a href="https://www.sps.ed.ac.uk/news-events/events/event-categories/seminar-series">Sociology Seminar Lecture Series</a> at the <a href="https://www.sps.ed.ac.uk/">School of Social and Political Science, The University of Edinburgh</a>. The talk will be held at the Violet Laidlaw Room, Chrystal Macmillan Building and online.</p>

<p>To register for the hybrid in-person and online talk, please <a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/of-eyebrows-moustaches-and-revolutionary-spirit-tickets-1003712520167">book your space via Eventbrite</a>.</p>

<p>Abstract:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Lu Xun is seen as the founding father of modern Chinese literature; thanks to the propagandistic efforts of the Chinese Communist Party, he was posthumously framed as a revolutionary fighter wielding his pen for the sake of the nation, and the revolution. This (re-)framing rested on political speeches appropriating the famous intellectual, on depictions of the author on propaganda posters, as well as on adaptations of his person and his works into Chinese comics (lianhuanhua连环画). In my presentation, I will sketch this process and argue that comics, as a medium combining text and image, were particularly well suited to this end, quite literally framing Lu Xun and his works from different viewpoints. As adaptations, lianhuanhua represent distinct readings of famous literary works – and as a genre of “pulp fiction”, they reached massive audiences, thus impacting how large parts of the Chinese population would read Lu Xun. I will show how lianhuanhua had their part in the styling of Lu Xun into a devoted revolutionary. Yet, time and again, lianhuanhua moved beyond the narrow reading of the CCP’s Luxunology, thus demonstrating that as a genre it is particularly well-suited to move beyond the narrow frames of official ideology, and that the texts of Lu Xun themselves defy easy readings and appropriations through Party ideology. Core to this are the ambivalences inscribed into the texts of Lu Xun, as well as the depictions of his eyebrows and moustache.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On 9 October 2024 at 11:00 - 12:30, ChinaComx PI Lena Henningsen will deliver a talk titled “Of Eyebrows, Moustaches and Revolutionary Spirit” as part of the Sociology Seminar Lecture Series at the School of Social and Political Science, The University of Edinburgh. The talk will be held at the Violet Laidlaw Room, Chrystal Macmillan Building and online.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Lena-Edinburgh2024.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Lena-Edinburgh2024.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Damian Mandzunowski and Lena Henningsen to Present on ChinaComx at the NY Comics Symposium on 24 September</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/09/04/LenaDamianNewYork.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Damian Mandzunowski and Lena Henningsen to Present on ChinaComx at the NY Comics Symposium on 24 September" /><published>2024-09-04T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-09-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/09/04/LenaDamianNewYork</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/09/04/LenaDamianNewYork.html"><![CDATA[<p>As the 399th talk delivered at the <a href="https://nycomicssymposium.wordpress.com/">NY Comics &amp; Picture-story Symposium</a>, Damian Mandzunowski and Lena Henningsen will introduce Chinese comics and the ChinaComx project on Tuesday, 24 Sept. 2024, at 9 pm Heidelberg time / 3 pm New York time. For more, see <a href="https://nycomicssymposium.wordpress.com/damian-mandzunowski-lena-henningsen-sept-24-2024-at-3pm-et-online/">here</a>.</p>

<p>To register for the online talk via zoom, please email <a href="mailto:comicssymposium@gmail.com">comicssymposium@gmail.com</a>.</p>

<p>Their talk is titled <strong>Beyond Captain America and Akira: Heroes and Villains in Chinese Comics and Caricature</strong>,  abstract:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Comics are a global medium with local variations and characteristics, emanating from different historical, cultural, social, political, and economic contexts. Putting the many differences aside, many forms of comics often share high popularity, expressive visuals and a focus on positive and negative role models. In this presentation, we therefore propose to look at Chinese comics (lianhuanhua) and caricature (manhua) through the lens of heroes and villains to offer both a general overview of these visual media and a specific examination of one of its core tropes. We will show how the era of high Maoism of the 1960s-1970s was also a heyday of the lianhuanhua genre as it was widely used as a tool for education and propaganda. Contrary to popular belief, also throughout the early Reform Era of the 1980s, lianhuanhua continued to shape prototypes of ideological heroes and villains, rendering all kinds of role models easy to detect. At the same time, however, Chinese comics began to critically re-examine the Maoist years, adapted (officially and bootleg) Hollywood blockbusters, and to, employ a fuller repertoire of expressive and ambivalent visual techniques, including pencil drawing, oil painting, traditional Chinese papercut and watercolors, or woodcut inspired by European modernism, thus undermining the previously clear-cut notions of what makes a hero (or villain) and they would have to look like. And although lianhuanhua as a particular medium-specific type of Chinese comics mostly faded away toward the end of the century, these handy pocket-sized booklets were shared among children and adults alike to be read at street stall libraries or at work units after hours for over seven decades. With an estimated 50.000 unique titles published since 1949 and one-in-three new books published in 1986 being a lianhuanhua, Chinese comics deserve broader recognition and scholarly interest both as distinct genre and area of academic research.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As the 399th talk delivered at the NY Comics &amp; Picture-story Symposium, Damian Mandzunowski and Lena Henningsen will introduce Chinese comics and the ChinaComx project on Tuesday, 24 Sept. 2024, at 9 pm Heidelberg time / 3 pm New York time. For more, see here.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/NY_fall-2024_symposium.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/NY_fall-2024_symposium.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">New Research Article on Caricatures of Jiang Qing co-written by Damian Mandzunowski</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/08/02/JiangQing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Research Article on Caricatures of Jiang Qing co-written by Damian Mandzunowski" /><published>2024-08-02T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-08-02T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/08/02/JiangQing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/08/02/JiangQing.html"><![CDATA[<p>A new research article jointly written by <a href="https://crsm.uw.edu.pl/staff/dr-laura-pozzi/">Laura Pozzi</a> and ChinaComx researcher <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Damian-Mandzunowski">Damian Mandzunowski</a> has been published in the <a href="https://read.dukeupress.edu/positions/article-abstract/32/3/539/389998/Jiang-Qing-the-Iconic-Anti-icon-Visual-Dissection?redirectedFrom=fulltext">August 2024 issue</a> of <em>positions: asia critique</em>.</p>

<p>The article is now also available to read/download via project muse <a href="https://muse.jhu.edu/pub/4/article/934949">here</a>.</p>

<p>Article abstract:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This article examines how, in the years following the end of the Cultural Revolution (1966 – 76), Jiang Qing 江青 (1914 – 91) became a negative icon of a liberated woman in high office in the People’s Republic of China (PRC). During the Cultural Revolution, Jiang Qing transformed herself into a model female political leader. After her arrest in 1976, however, political caricatures systematically deconstructed her curated image by transforming her into the antithesis of the ideal powerful woman in a socialist society. Since a model liberated female politician was not yet available, Jiang Qing served as an “iconic anti-icon” of women in politics under state socialism. Acknowledging the importance of Jiang Qing as a historical figure in Maoist China, this article analyzes how post – Cultural Revolution caricatures of her provide us with an understanding of the Chinese Communist Party’s anxieties about women in power, and it raises questions about the absence of an iconic woman-leader in the PRC’s political visual culture despite years of campaigning to achieve women’s liberation.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A new research article jointly written by Laura Pozzi and ChinaComx researcher Damian Mandzunowski has been published in the August 2024 issue of positions: asia critique.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/PozziMandzunowski_FIG8.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/PozziMandzunowski_FIG8.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">ChinaComx to Present at a Digital Humanities in East Asian Studies Conference in Berlin on 8-12 July</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/06/19/DSEA-Berlin.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ChinaComx to Present at a Digital Humanities in East Asian Studies Conference in Berlin on 8-12 July" /><published>2024-06-19T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-06-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/06/19/DSEA-Berlin</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/06/19/DSEA-Berlin.html"><![CDATA[<p>ChinaComx researchers Aijia Zhang and Damian Mandzunowski will take part in the workshops and conference <a href="https://www.mpiwg-berlin.mpg.de/event/charting-european-d-sea">Charting the European D-SEA: Digital Scholarship in East Asian Studies</a> jointly organied by the <a href="https://www.mpiwg-berlin.mpg.de/">Max Planck Institute for the History of Science</a> and the <a href="https://staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/">Berlin State Library – Prussian Cultural Heritage</a>, to be held on 8-12 July 2024 in Berlin.</p>

<p>Damian will also present on 12 July a joint paper titled “<strong>Beyond Manga and Marvel: Digitally Approaching Chinese Comics (Lianhuanhua)</strong>,” which provides overview of the DH scope of ChinaComx – paper abstract:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For many years now digital humanities (DH) scholars have approached graphic narratives such as comics as primary sources for digitally enhanced academic engagements with culture, history, or society. However, extant literature mainly focuses on US-American comic books, Japanese manga, or French/Belgian bandes dessinées. Lianhuanhua, a type of Chinese comics mostly consisting of a single image panel with a few lines of text below, are by and large overlooked—and this despite their untapped potential as novel sources for DH scholarship. Through the ERC-funded research project “Comics Culture in the People’s Republic of China (ChinaComx)” we aim to expand the related fields by introducing lianhuanhua as a new source employing digital tools, programming, and computer vision. While contemporary Chinese webcomics can be downloaded and read on mobile devices, earlier lianhuanhua were produced on low quality paper and in small pocket-size format resulting in a distinct instability of the books. Their materiality is a key characteristic of this medium, defining it both as a distinct type of graphic narrative while also pointing toward shared elements with other comics of different origins. Making use of the digitized CATS-Seifert Collection of Chinese Comics at Heidelberg University consisting of over 3000 unique lianhuanhua, ChinaComx makes extensive use of digitizing the physical records, advanced OCR-ing, and AI-assisted automatized translation of large datasets consisting of the image-text dyads. Furthermore, we also plan to do DH aided visual analyses, using methods such as visual language processing or network analysis, to delve into issues such scene composition, stylometry or genre defining visual features of lianhuanhua. The results of these, collected and made available to the public via an OA digital database, will not only allow non-Chinese speakers to read and engage with lianhuanhua, but they will also present engaging case studies to be picked up and expanded by other DH scholars. ChinaComx will thus also digitally preserve lianhuanhua and make them available for university and school classroom use. In this proposed presentation, we will give an overview of the ChinaComx sources, DH approaches and potential issues related to ethics and longevity of digital scholarship on Chinese comics.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>See the complete workshops program and abstracts <a href="https://wg-cloud.gnz.mpg.de/s/dJ8sbWRzpXfze3L">here</a>, and the conference program and abstracts <a href="https://wg-cloud.gnz.mpg.de/s/iPgfsYERyzSZzEw">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[ChinaComx researchers Aijia Zhang and Damian Mandzunowski will take part in the workshops and conference Charting the European D-SEA: Digital Scholarship in East Asian Studies jointly organied by the Max Planck Institute for the History of Science and the Berlin State Library – Prussian Cultural Heritage, to be held on 8-12 July 2024 in Berlin.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/D-SEA-2024.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/D-SEA-2024.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Lena Henningsen to Present at the 2024 IÜD Showcase in Heidelberg on 3 July</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/06/19/LenaIUeD.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lena Henningsen to Present at the 2024 IÜD Showcase in Heidelberg on 3 July" /><published>2024-06-19T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-06-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/06/19/LenaIUeD</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/06/19/LenaIUeD.html"><![CDATA[<p>ChinaComx PI, Lena Henningsen, will present on the realm of translating Chinese comics at the <a href="https://www.uni-heidelberg.de/fakultaeten/neuphil/iask/sued/imstudium/showcase_fachkonferenz.html">ShowCase Dolmetschwissenschaft Live</a> at the Institut für Übersetzen und Dolmetschen (Institute for Translation and Interpreting) at Heidelberg University, in the Konferenzsaal II at Plöck 57A, on 3 July.</p>

<p>The talk is titled “LIANHUANHUA (连环画): CHINESE COMICS IN TRANSLATION AND IN TRANSCULTURAL PERSPECTIVE” and will be at 14:15. For direct access to the Zoom stream, click <a href="https://us06web.zoom.us/j/88926559960?pwd=VgfTLktNIfHUfNfzSpQ1lM4hSsvAmi.1">here</a>.</p>

<p>The conference will be simultaneously translated into seven languages—English, French, Italian, Japanese, Portuguese, Russian, and Spanish—so even if you’re not familiar with German, do tune in! Click <a href="../assets/images/Showcase-HD-2024.pdf">here</a> for the conference poster and program.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[ChinaComx PI, Lena Henningsen, will present on the realm of translating Chinese comics at the ShowCase Dolmetschwissenschaft Live at the Institut für Übersetzen und Dolmetschen (Institute for Translation and Interpreting) at Heidelberg University, in the Konferenzsaal II at Plöck 57A, on 3 July.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Showcase-HD-2024.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Showcase-HD-2024.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Damian Mandzunowski Presenting at the Political Lives in Socialist China Conference, 10-12 June in Paris</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/05/30/DamianParis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Damian Mandzunowski Presenting at the Political Lives in Socialist China Conference, 10-12 June in Paris" /><published>2024-05-30T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-30T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/05/30/DamianParis</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/05/30/DamianParis.html"><![CDATA[<p>ChinaComx researcher Damian Mandzunowski will present a paper titled <strong>Collective Reading Practices After the Cultural Revolution</strong> at the conference <a href="https://www.ehess.fr/fr/colloque/political-lives-socialist-china">Political Lives in Socialist China</a> organized by <a href="https://www.ehess.fr/fr/personne/isabelle-thireau">Isabelle Thireau, CNRS/EHESS, CCJ-CECMC</a> and <a href="https://history.berkeley.edu/puck-engman">Puck Engman, Center for Chinese Studies at UC Berkeley</a> and held at the EHESS: École des hautes études en sciences sociales in Paris on 10-12 June 2024. Click <a href="../assets/images/PoliticalLivesInSocialistChina.pdf">here</a> for the program.</p>

<p>His paper abstract:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Conventional understanding of post-Cultural Revolution China suggests a gradual but steady shift from politics to production. However, did politics truly vanish, or did one form of the political replace another? This paper takes a case study approach, examining a selection of mid-1970s mass-reading campaigns, to inquire how political study continued to shape the daily lives of workers and cadres. The mass phase of the Cultural Revolution, due to the excesses of group readings of confessions and accusations at struggle sessions, rendered texts relevant to virtually everyone. Once it was over by the early-1970s, it gave way again to more systematically organized practices of collective reading akin to those functioning in the PRC since 1949. While study materials swiftly adapted to current political goals, a system of incentives and penalties ensured regular participation. Detailed descriptions from above further facilitated a tightly controlled guidance. State propaganda hence put much effort in utilizing collective reading practices to convey notions of statehood, class struggle, and mass society. At the same time, collective readers ultimately choose their own participation strategies ranging from enthusiastic activism through careful ignorance to blatant disruption. Examining the intertwined relationship between collective reading practices, the resurgence of the state apparatus, and the intra-party struggles over Mao’s succession illustrates how the lived experience of politics retained its significance also within the context of state socialist promotion of production.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[ChinaComx researcher Damian Mandzunowski will present a paper titled Collective Reading Practices After the Cultural Revolution at the conference Political Lives in Socialist China organized by Isabelle Thireau, CNRS/EHESS, CCJ-CECMC and Puck Engman, Center for Chinese Studies at UC Berkeley and held at the EHESS: École des hautes études en sciences sociales in Paris on 10-12 June 2024. Click here for the program.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/PoliticalLivesInSocialistChina.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/PoliticalLivesInSocialistChina.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Lena Henningsen to Present at the Rethinking Modern Chinese Elites Conference in Aix-Marseille on 10-12 June</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/05/12/LenaAix.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lena Henningsen to Present at the Rethinking Modern Chinese Elites Conference in Aix-Marseille on 10-12 June" /><published>2024-05-12T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/05/12/LenaAix</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/05/12/LenaAix.html"><![CDATA[<p>ChinaComx PI, Lena Henningsen, will present a paper at the conference <a href="https://china-conference.univ-amu.fr/">Rethinking Modern Chinese Elites – From Print to Computational Methods: Sources, Languages, and Interdisciplinarity</a> organized by the <a href="https://www.enpchina.eu/">Elites, Networks and Power in Modern China project</a> at Aix-Marseiile University on 10-12 June 2024.</p>

<p>Her paper abstract:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>It is a truism that Chinese culture is a culture of reading; and – with the exception of the time of high socialism – reading has always been a marker of cultural capital. Yet, how exactly did reading impact on individuals, society and the larger developments and transformations in Chinese history? What did Chinese citizens read when, why, and how? In how far was reading a transformative act for everyone – and what readings were limited to certain groups, to intellectual, literary or political elites? Studying historical reading practices poses a number of methodological problems, not least because it is very often a private, even intimate activity of which little historical documents exist. Extant accounts – often autobiographical sources – are ephemeral, anecdotal, and very often vague. To analyze reading practices during China’s long 1970s quantitatively, we developed the ReadAct database (https://readchina.github.io/readact.html) chronicling concrete historical reading acts as recorded in a broad array of life writing sources. In this paper, I will present findings from the database, taking into account the biases and blind spots in the sources and in the database. Considering that most accounts were written by urban educated youth sent to the countryside and considering what they chose to write about in their accounts (and what to leave out) the database chronicles how much of the social, literary and intellectual change commonly associated with the early years of the reform era had its origins in the reading quests of the rusticated educated youth. Moreover, these reading quests also anticipate how as a group these youths – many of them social and political outcasts at the time – would transform into the literary, cultural and / or intellectual elite of the early reform years.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[ChinaComx PI, Lena Henningsen, will present a paper at the conference Rethinking Modern Chinese Elites – From Print to Computational Methods: Sources, Languages, and Interdisciplinarity organized by the Elites, Networks and Power in Modern China project at Aix-Marseiile University on 10-12 June 2024.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/RMCE-2024.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/RMCE-2024.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The 2024 Conference of the German Chinese Teacher’s Association Coorganized by ChinaComx</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/04/28/Fachtagung2024.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The 2024 Conference of the German Chinese Teacher’s Association Coorganized by ChinaComx" /><published>2024-04-28T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-04-28T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/04/28/Fachtagung2024</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/04/28/Fachtagung2024.html"><![CDATA[<p>ChinaComx is coorganising this year’s <a href="https://www.cats.uni-heidelberg.de/medien/fach23.html">conference of the German Chinese teacher’s association - Fachverband Chinesisch e.V.</a>. The trilingual conference is entitled “Crossing Borders, Teaching China Competence” and will be held at Heidelberg’s Center for Asian and Transcultural Studies. For the program in PDF, click <a href="ADD PDF">here</a>.</p>

<p>Lena Henningsen will give a presentation on the ChinaComx translation project and its involvement in classroom settings: How translating comics is a meaningful and rewarding experience for students of Chinese – and how translated comics can be meaningfully integrated into the teaching about Chinese history, society, culture and literature among different students, ranging from middle schools to universities.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[ChinaComx is coorganising this year’s conference of the German Chinese teacher’s association - Fachverband Chinesisch e.V.. The trilingual conference is entitled “Crossing Borders, Teaching China Competence” and will be held at Heidelberg’s Center for Asian and Transcultural Studies. For the program in PDF, click here.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Fachtagung2024.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Fachtagung2024.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Lena Henningsen to Present ChinaComx at the CATS-Forum 2024</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/01/25/CATSforum2024.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lena Henningsen to Present ChinaComx at the CATS-Forum 2024" /><published>2024-01-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/01/25/CATSforum2024</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/01/25/CATSforum2024.html"><![CDATA[<p>To give a first overview of the ChinaComx project outline, its goals, and research ideas, our PI, Lena Henningsen, will give a presentation at the CATS-Forum held on Friday 26 January 2024, between 11 am (c.t.) – ca. 2 pm, in room 400.02.12 in the <a href="https://www.asia-europe.uni-heidelberg.de/en">Karl Jaspers Centre</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[To give a first overview of the ChinaComx project outline, its goals, and research ideas, our PI, Lena Henningsen, will give a presentation at the CATS-Forum held on Friday 26 January 2024, between 11 am (c.t.) – ca. 2 pm, in room 400.02.12 in the Karl Jaspers Centre.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/CATS-Forum2024.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/CATS-Forum2024.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>