<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-08-25T13:55:52+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">ChinaComx</title><subtitle>Comics Culture in the People&apos;s Republic of China</subtitle><entry><title type="html">PUBLICATION ALERT: Mandzunowski reviews Du, Animated Encounters (University of Hawaiʻi Press, 2019)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/08/20/DamianAnimationReview.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PUBLICATION ALERT: Mandzunowski reviews Du, Animated Encounters (University of Hawaiʻi Press, 2019)" /><published>2025-08-20T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-08-20T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/08/20/DamianAnimationReview</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/08/20/DamianAnimationReview.html"><![CDATA[<p>A review article by ChinaComx Postdoc <a href="https://chinacomx.github.io/team/damian/">Damian Mandzunowski</a> of Daisy Yan Du’s <em>Animated Encounters: Transnational Movements of Chinese Animation, 1940s-1970s</em> (University of Hawaiʻi Press, 2019) is now published on the Animation Studies 2.0 blog, read it <a href="https://blog.animationstudies.org/?p=7281">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A review article by ChinaComx Postdoc Damian Mandzunowski of Daisy Yan Du’s Animated Encounters: Transnational Movements of Chinese Animation, 1940s-1970s (University of Hawaiʻi Press, 2019) is now published on the Animation Studies 2.0 blog, read it here.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/animationstudies2.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/animationstudies2.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">PUBLICATION ALERT: Yearbook of the German Assoc. of Chinese Studies (DVCS) 18, ed. by Henningsen, Leese, and Mandzunowski</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/07/30/DVCS18.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PUBLICATION ALERT: Yearbook of the German Assoc. of Chinese Studies (DVCS) 18, ed. by Henningsen, Leese, and Mandzunowski" /><published>2025-07-30T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-07-30T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/07/30/DVCS18</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/07/30/DVCS18.html"><![CDATA[<p>The most recent yearbook of the <a href="https://www.dvcs.eu/index_en.php">German Association of Chinese Studies (Deutsche Vereinigung für Chinastudien, DVCS)</a>, edited by ChinaComx PI, <a href="https://chinacomx.github.io/team/lena/">Lena Henningsen</a>, <a href="https://uni-freiburg.de/sinologie/einrichtung-und-personen/daniel-leese/">Daniel Leese</a>, and ChinaComx Postdoc, <a href="https://chinacomx.github.io/team/damian/">Damian Mandzunowski</a>, has just been published. It is the outcome of the <a href="https://dvcs2021.github.io/">2021 annual DVCS conference</a> that we jointly organized in Freiburg.</p>

<p>See <a href="https://www.harrassowitz-verlag.de/Wissensasymmetrien/titel_8450.ahtml">the publisher’s website</a> for all the details, or click <a href="/assets/images/978-3-447-12360-0_Inhaltsverzeichnis.pdf" download="">here</a> to download the table of contents in PDF.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The most recent yearbook of the German Association of Chinese Studies (Deutsche Vereinigung für Chinastudien, DVCS), edited by ChinaComx PI, Lena Henningsen, Daniel Leese, and ChinaComx Postdoc, Damian Mandzunowski, has just been published. It is the outcome of the 2021 annual DVCS conference that we jointly organized in Freiburg.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/978-3-447-12360-0.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/978-3-447-12360-0.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Graduate Workshop ‘Caricature and Comics in a Global Context’ on 22 July in Heidelberg</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/07/07/JulyGraduateWorkshop.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Graduate Workshop ‘Caricature and Comics in a Global Context’ on 22 July in Heidelberg" /><published>2025-07-07T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-07-07T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/07/07/JulyGraduateWorkshop</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/07/07/JulyGraduateWorkshop.html"><![CDATA[<p>We are cordially inviting you to join a graduate workshop titled <strong>Caricature and Comics in a Global Context: Brazil, Turkey, Iran, Algeria, China, and Taiwan</strong> to be held on <strong>22 July 2025</strong> between <strong>8:45 and 18:30</strong> at the <strong>Seminarraum Werkstatt in <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/4j2ZWLmW9QuP6bYx6">Albert-Ueberle-Weg 3-5</a></strong>.</p>

<p>We especially invite scholars and students to the keynote lecture, delivered by ChinaComx Visiting Scholar <a href="https://www.transatlantic-cultures.org/fr/author/lima-gomes">Ivan Gomes</a> (Federal University of Goiás) at 14:00, see below for poster and abstract.</p>

<p>For the full conference program, click <a href="/assets/images/CaricatureAndComicsInAGlobalContext-program.pdf" download="">here</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/IvanGomesKeynote-poster.jpg" alt="Keynote lecture by Ivan Gomes on 22 July at 14:00" /></p>

<p><strong>In Search of Brazilian Culture through Post-Mao China: Notes on an Illustrated Report by the Brazilian Cartoonist Henfil (1977-1980)</strong></p>
<blockquote>
  <p>In 1977, Brazilian cartoonist Henfil undertook a two-week visit to China, an experience he documented in a series of newspaper articles that were subsequently compiled into a book. <em>Henfil na China (antes da Coca-Cola)</em> constitutes not only a rare moment of an active engagement between the Brazilian and Chinese comics traditions but is also part of a broader historical context marked by Latin American intellectual and artistic engagements with China. Additionally, the work reflects the transnational ambitions of a number of Brazilian cartoonists who, during the military dictatorship (1964–1985), sought to establish international networks as a means of cultural and political resistance. This presentation offers a preliminary investigation into these themes, drawing on concepts such as transnationalism in comics and world literature to situate Henfil’s production within the Brazilian comics culture of the 1970s - a field shaped by efforts to navigate a print market constrained by censorship and authoritarian control. I argue that Henfil na China embodies a condition of transit by challenging conventional categorizations, as it brings together cartoons, illustrations, photographs, and travel writing within a single hybrid format.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The workshop is co-organized by ChinaComx PI, <a href="https://chinacomx.github.io/team/lena/">Lena Henningsen</a>, and <a href="https://www.ori.uni-heidelberg.de/islamwissenschaft/institut/mitarbeiter/kollatz.html#forschungsgebiet">Anna Kollatz</a>, the co-PI of the research project <a href="https://caricatures.hypotheses.org/499">“Wo ist der Witz? Karikaturen als Kommunikationssphäre im spät- und postosmanischen Kontext”</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are cordially inviting you to join a graduate workshop titled Caricature and Comics in a Global Context: Brazil, Turkey, Iran, Algeria, China, and Taiwan to be held on 22 July 2025 between 8:45 and 18:30 at the Seminarraum Werkstatt in Albert-Ueberle-Weg 3-5.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/CaricatureAndComicsInAGlobalContext-poster.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/CaricatureAndComicsInAGlobalContext-poster.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Lena Henningsen and Damian Mandzunowski to Present at the ‘Competing for the People’s Eyes and Ears from Mao to Xi’ Symposium, 27-28 June in Prague</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/06/15/LenaDamianPrague.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lena Henningsen and Damian Mandzunowski to Present at the ‘Competing for the People’s Eyes and Ears from Mao to Xi’ Symposium, 27-28 June in Prague" /><published>2025-06-15T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-06-15T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/06/15/LenaDamianPrague</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/06/15/LenaDamianPrague.html"><![CDATA[<p>ChinaComx PI, <a href="https://chinacomx.github.io/team/lena/">Lena Henningsen</a>, and postdoc researcher, <a href="https://chinacomx.github.io/team/damian/">Damian Mandzunowski</a>, are about to participate in an international symposium on transformations of cultural life in the PRC titled <a href="https://ksi.ff.cuni.cz/en/research/transformations-of-cultural-life-in-the-prc/">Competing for the people’s eyes and ears from Mao to Xi: transformations of cultural life in the PRC</a> to be held at <a href="https://ksi.ff.cuni.cz/en/">Department of Sinology, Faculty of Arts, Charles University</a> and <a href="http://www.cckf.org/en/about/structure/overseas_center/Charles_University">Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation International Sinological Centre at Charles University</a> on June 27–28, 2025.</p>

<p>In their respective papers, both Lena and Damian will discuss the silences, sounds, and noises of lianhuanhua—albeit in very different ways and to very differing conclusions.</p>

<p>For the conference program, see <a href="https://ksi.ff.cuni.cz/en/research/transformations-of-cultural-life-in-the-prc/">here</a>, and read on for the two paper abstracts below:</p>

<p><strong>Lena Henningsen (Heidelberg University), “Sounds of Silence: Sonic Comic Stories amid the Noises of Maoist China”</strong></p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Western comic art has been described as audiovisual. The depiction of noise such as music emanating from a gramophone or of stomping feet, as Eike Exner argues, proved formative for the rise of modern comics in the US. If audiovisual elements are constitutive for the medium of comics, an inquiry into the sonic qualities of lianhuanhua – the pocket size comics genre popular throughout the 20th century – suggests itself; even more so when the context of their consumption, a China immersed in the rumpus of the revolution, is also taken into the account. Throughout the Mao era, lianhuanhua were employed to mobilize readers for the revolution and to instill them with revolutionary fervor, making full use of the text and images in these comics. Often, lianhuanhua told stories of revolutionary heroes and of ferocious fights against the enemies of the revolution. However, I argue that lianhuanhua are much less noisy than their foreign counterparts: speech bubbles exist, but to a lesser extent than in Western comics; sound is not visualized on the panels; pastoral backgrounds to the action often give scenes a notion of peace and quiet; very often, protagonists are depicted solitarily and absorbed in thought, or within small groups and in calm dialogue; even scenes depicting larger groups of people typically do not shout at their readers. Adding to these stylistic inquiries and their changes over time, I will also inquire into the contexts within which comics were read, arguing that this (relative) silence offered readers an escape into an atmosphere of serenity and quietness. This, I contend, added to the popularity of the genre in a Maoist China flooded with the noises of propaganda.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>Damian Mandzunowski (Heidelberg University), “Revolutionary Onomatopoeia: Soundscapes in/of Chinese Comics of the Mao Era”</strong></p>
<blockquote>
  <p>A significant portion of the sonic and visual stimuli capturing people’s attention in the People’s Republic of China (PRC) was intermedial. Films often included subtitles indicating how to sing along; radio broadcasts of important editorials encouraged listeners to read along; propaganda posters depicted scenes to be staged and re-enacted. This paper examines another such phenomenon: the depiction of onomatopoeia, interjections, and other expressions of sound in Chinese comics (lianhuanhua) of the Mao era (1949–1976). These popular booklets, enjoyed by millions of children and adults alike, frequently included scenes of evocation, explosions, screams, singing, radio listening, talking, or whispering, but also of natural sounds such as animals chirping or belling and elements like wind, rivers, and forests. Conversely, lianhuanhua functioned as a very “loud” medium: these supposedly silent booklets were often read aloud at street bookstalls or in mobile libraries by groups of children, or by mothers at bedtime. All this was accompanied by the sounds of flipping pages, gasps at plot twists, and the voices of the readers. How did visualised sound relate to image, text, meaning, and reception of lianhuanhua? What changes and continuities in these depictions can be traced over the decades? And which sounds made it into the visual canon of revolutionary onomatopoeia—and which not? This paper offers a first exploration of the intermediality of sound and image in lianhuanhua. By taking a set of exemplary comics as a case study, it explores how popular culture under state socialism drew upon familiar forms while creating indigenous approaches to visualizing soundscapes. It also seeks to enhance our understanding of one of the most influential media in the daily lives of people under state socialism. Expanding beyond the printed form, this paper further highlights lianhuanhua’s cultural significance during a transformative era of modern Chinese history when sound and image converged.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[ChinaComx PI, Lena Henningsen, and postdoc researcher, Damian Mandzunowski, are about to participate in an international symposium on transformations of cultural life in the PRC titled Competing for the people’s eyes and ears from Mao to Xi: transformations of cultural life in the PRC to be held at Department of Sinology, Faculty of Arts, Charles University and Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation International Sinological Centre at Charles University on June 27–28, 2025.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/prague2025.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/prague2025.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">PUBLICATION ALERT: Lena Henningsen’s article on the Lianhuanhua Death(s) of Lu Xun in Closure</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/05/29/LenaClosure.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PUBLICATION ALERT: Lena Henningsen’s article on the Lianhuanhua Death(s) of Lu Xun in Closure" /><published>2025-05-29T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-05-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/05/29/LenaClosure</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/05/29/LenaClosure.html"><![CDATA[<p>The recent edition of <em>Closure. Kieler Journal für Comicforschung</em>—a leading German comics studies journal—includes a new article by Lena Henningsen, ChinaComx PI, on the rich imagery of the death of Lu Xun within Chinese lianhuanhua comics. Navigating questions of legacy and visual memory, the article offers a glimpse into the larger project of Chinese Lu Xun comics that Lena is advancing within ChinaComx.</p>

<p>Go to the journal’s webiste <a href="http://www.closure.uni-kiel.de/closure11/henningsen">here</a> to read the article, or directly download a PDF by clicking  <a href="/assets/images/closure11_henningsen.pdf" download="">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The recent edition of Closure. Kieler Journal für Comicforschung—a leading German comics studies journal—includes a new article by Lena Henningsen, ChinaComx PI, on the rich imagery of the death of Lu Xun within Chinese lianhuanhua comics. Navigating questions of legacy and visual memory, the article offers a glimpse into the larger project of Chinese Lu Xun comics that Lena is advancing within ChinaComx.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/LenaClosure.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/LenaClosure.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Conference Report by Nick Stember on the ChinaComx Workshop ‘Lianhuanhua as Method’!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/05/15/LianhuanhuaAsMethodReport.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Conference Report by Nick Stember on the ChinaComx Workshop ‘Lianhuanhua as Method’!" /><published>2025-05-15T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-05-15T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/05/15/LianhuanhuaAsMethodReport</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/05/15/LianhuanhuaAsMethodReport.html"><![CDATA[<p>After a bit over a year since the ChinaComx project commenced, and just over half a year after the team was assembled and our daily work on all things lianhuanhua began, we <a href="https://chinacomx.github.io/jekyll/update/2025/04/10/LianhuanhuaAsMethod.html">welcomed</a> to Heidelberg 18 scholars of Chinese (and Asian) cartoon, caricature, comics, lianhuanhua, and other related forms of pictorial narratives for an intensively productive albeit fun workshop on 24-26 April 2025.</p>

<p>One of the presenters and close friend of the project, <a href="https://www.nickstember.com/">Nick Stember</a>, himself a translator and historian of Chinese literature and popular culture who has been writing extensively on the topic of Chinese comics and visual print and screen cultures more broadly for over a decade now, contributed a post-workshop summary. We thank Nick for his initiative and provide the summary here in full length, as, while written from the point of view of one of the participants and voicing some personal reflections from the author, it gives back adequately the scope and variety of presentations and conversations heard during the ChinaComx “Lianhuanhua as Method” workshop.</p>

<p>If we were to select the one key observation of the workshop it perhaps would be that to position a distinct medium as the defining element of inquiry indeed does not imply a limitation or constraint; much to the contrary, and as we believe is also tangible from the following conference report, by putting lianhuanhua centerstage we open up a whole new horizon of possibilities to reading Chinese culture, politics, society, literature, and history.</p>

<p>And now on to Nick Stember’s summary of the workshop——and if you would like to continue the discussion, please do reach out to us using the website’s <a href="https://chinacomx.github.io/contact/">contact form</a>!</p>

<hr />

<h1 id="lianhuanhua-as-method-a-chinacomx-workshop-24-26-april-20025-heidelberg">Lianhuanhua as Method: A ChinaComx Workshop, 24-26 April 20025, Heidelberg</h1>
<h3 id="conference-report-by-nick-stember">conference report by Nick Stember*</h3>
<p>Having spent a very productive three days getting to geek out over lianhuanhua (and Chinese comics more broadly) at the ChinaComx “Lianhuanhua as Method” workshop, I wanted to take a moment to provide a quick summary of the papers that were presented and touch on some of the recurring topics and themes. This seems particularly appropriate given that, as a relatively small and still emerging field, there is still a great deal of work to be done to define the parameters of our research—which, as it happens was one of the goals of the workshop, which included papers on topics related to lianhuanhua such as (to give just two examples) manhua and cigarette cards. It is my hope also, that by sharing resources, strategies, and findings with our colleagues around the world who are making their own contributions to the study of this distinct area of cultural production, we can play a small part in ‘paying forward’ the generosity of early pioneers in the field, chief among them <a href="https://visarts.ucsd.edu/people/faculty/kuiyi-shen.html">Kuiyi Shen</a>, <a href="https://history-of-art.osu.edu/people/andrews.2">Julia Andrews</a>, <a href="https://www.colgate.edu/about/directory/jcrespi">John Crespi</a>, <a href="https://www.e-aoi.uzh.ch/apps/china-west/entities/4780">Ellen Johnston Laing</a>, <a href="https://www.irancartoon.com/site/interview/interview-with-professor-john-a-lent">John Lent</a>, <a href="https://www.upress.state.ms.us/Contributors/X/Xu-Ying">Xu Ying</a>, and <a href="https://www.soas.ac.uk/about/paul-bevan">Paul Bevan</a>.</p>

<p>It was especially appropriate, therefore, that the workshop opened with a keynote from just such a generous pioneer, with <a href="https://www.zo.uni-heidelberg.de/sinologie/institute/staff/mittler/">Barbara Mittler</a> presenting a paper titled ‘Chained Pictures and Chained by Pictures,’ subtitled ‘Comics and Cultural Revolutions in China.’ As the talk began, in nod to the organizers, Mittler corrected the latter to read ‘Lianhuanhua and Cultural Revolutions in China,’ bringing to the fore one of the questions of definitions and terminology, which would become one of the recurring themes of the workshop. Building on Walter Benjamin’s provocative claim that “only dialectical images are genuinely historical,” Mittler drew on the example of Zhao Hongben’s celebrated lianhuanhua adaptation of ‘Sun Wukong Thrice Defeats the White Bone Demon’ to show how the changes which were made to editions published before and after the Cultural Revolution reflect the aesthetic hegemony of the ‘Three Represents’ as part of the evolving ideology of Maoist orthodoxy.</p>

<p>This provocative presentation set the stage for the first panel the following day, beginning with my paper, titled ‘Picture Stories: Delimiting the Generic Boundaries of Taste in Lianhuanhua in the 1950s PRC.’ In it, I drew on an editorial published in the inaugural issue of <em>Picture Stories</em> (Lianhuanhua bao) to highlight some of the tensions over poor taste and violent, pornographic, and superstitious subject matter that carried over from the Republican era, and which would remain at the heart of the medium all the way up into the 1980s, a period which (as it happens) was the subject of my PhD thesis. This historical contextualization of lianhuanhua was paired with <a href="https://chinacomx.github.io/team/lena/">Lena Henningsen’s</a> theoretically nuanced discussion of ‘Approaching Lianhuanhua as Genre,’ in which she suggested that lianhuanhua can be understood as not just a medium, but further as genre (or grouping of genres), both contained within the larger super-category of comics (as we understand them today), and at the same time distinct from it.</p>

<p>In the question and answer session, meanwhile, Stephen Packard as discussant pointed to the question of affordances and limitations, inviting us to consider, “What questions does [treating lianhuanhua as a medium or genre] allow us to ask?”</p>

<p>It was this question that <a href="https://www.soas.ac.uk/about/avital-avina">Avital Avina</a> took up in the presentation of her paper, titled ‘Cigarette Cards Telling Stories: Tradeable Lianhuanhua?’ Taking a closer look at an even more neglected area of cultural production, Avina considered the humble cigarette card, which, as she demonstrated, served as much more than just an eye-catching collectible and marketing tool. Rather, Avina argued that the cigarette card encouraged a specific habitus of engagement in graphic narrative that was strikingly similar to the consumption and production of lianhuanhua — highlighting the same mix of high culture and low humor that characterize the comics of the pre- and post-Mao eras. Following on from this, <a href="https://chinacomx.github.io/team/damian/">Damian Mandzunowski</a> turned to the weird and wild world of instruction manual lianhuanhua, presenting a series of comics dedicated to the purchasing and maintenance of desirable home appliances, from television sets to refrigerators to bicycles. Observing that these products would have been out of reach for all but the most privileged and well-off of consumers, Mandzunowski made a provocative case for a parallel with the presentation of utopian plentitude that characterized the Great Leap Forward over twenty years earlier, and suggested that these texts can be read as‘manuals of instruction’ in the new cosmopolitanism and capitalist consumerism of the postsocialist period.</p>

<p>In his discussion of this panel, chair <a href="https://www.sinologie-goettingen.de/en/department/person/dr-harlan-david-chambers/">Harlan Chambers</a> touched on the production of leisure as a central concern of not only the two papers, but the topic of lianhuanhua as a whole, while at the same time cautioning us to not confuse historical repetition with historical continuity. In this regard, he pointed to the re-enclosure of women in the home as a place of abundance as a reversion, rather than a continuation of the radical Maoist politics of emancipation.</p>

<p>In the afternoon, the discussion of continuity and discontinuity continued with <a href="https://www.unibg.it/ugov/person/64892">Martina Caschera’s</a> paper ‘Transmedial Storytelling: Mu Ming’s 假⼿于⼈ Becoming an Italian Graphic Novel’ in which she introduced a recent adaption of a short story by the Chinese science fiction author Mu Ming into a graphic novel by the Italian writer Erica Benvenuti and illustrator Cristina Tomasini, as part of the Future Editions series edited by Francesco Verso. Caschera argued that this work represents an excellent example of the productive collaborations that can develop when graphic storytellers working in one tradition are invited to collaborate with Chinese authors to visually represent speculative futures.  Similarly, in her paper ‘Translating Lianhuanhua: Reflections on The Later Journey to the West for Translation Practices in Course,’ <a href="https://personen.uni-mainz.de/public/org/320/member/198548">Yun-jou Chen</a> shared her experience working with a group of German- and Chinese-speaking students to translate a lianhuanhua adaption of <em>Later Journey to the West</em> from the late 1980s. Chen suggested what made this class particularly effective as a learning exercise was the process of negotiation and advising that took place between students with differing linguistic and cultural backgrounds, resulting in two distinct translations.</p>

<p>As discussant, Lena Henningsen noted the unexpected challenges and opportunities that cross-cultural communication provides, particularly in regard to the interpretation of visual motifs and differing approaches to translation, as demonstrated in these two papers. She further shared that ChinaComx has several translations of lianhuanhua forthcoming on its website and encouraged Chen and her students (and indeed participants in the workshop as well) to submit their work for inclusion in this project.</p>

<p><a href="https://ksi.ff.cuni.cz/en/people/structure-and-staff/mariia-guleva/">Mariia Guleva</a> kicked off the next panel with her paper ‘When Cartoons Look Like Comics: Interpreting Standalone Manhua in Multi-panel Layouts,’ sharing examples of not only multi-panel manhua (cartoons) – in other words, comics strips – but also full-page spreads on related topics, designed to help readers make sense of otherwise ambiguous content. Drawing on Scott McCloud’s concept of closure, Neil Cohn’s ‘filling in the gaps,’ and Ernst Gombrich’s ‘projection into,’ Guleva observed that such juxtapositions often run the risk of confusing eulogies and criticism, providing examples of letters from readers complaining of just this. In the next paper, ‘Actions and Intentions: A Distant Reading of Lianhuanhua,’ <a href="https://chinacomx.github.io/team/aijia/">Aijia Zhang</a> took a different tack, providing a statistical analysis of an initial corpus of over 200 lianhuanhua using machine learning applied to the captions and other paratexts. In her preliminary findings, Zhang noted the prevalence of stories set in the War of Resistance Against Japan (1937–1945), highlighting the importance of patriotism and national sovereignty in these stories.</p>

<p>As discussant, <a href="https://www.su.se/english/profiles/jbern-1.259043">Jaqueline Berndt</a> urged us to reconsider the usefulness of ambiguity for political messaging and also encouraged the pairing of quantitative and qualitative analysis, observing that digital tools can obscure as much as they reveal.</p>

<p>For the second keynote, <a href="https://mekuwi.phil-fak.uni-koeln.de/en/personen/professor-innen/prof-dr-stephan-packard">Stephan Packard</a> presented his paper titled ‘Who Are These Panels For? Comparative Perspectives on Popular Sequential Art,’ providing a whirlwind tour of the contributions of media studies to the emerging field of comics studies over the past two decades. Beginning with the question ‘What does it mean to say that lianhuanhua are an object for comics studies?’ Packard introduced Dick Higgins’ concept of ‘intermedia,’ or the space that is opened up in works that bridge distinct media and genres. Provisionally then, Packard suggested that ‘popular sequential art’ could be used to refer to a loose network of associated terms and creative practices, from comics and lianhuanhua to manhua and cartoons. This multimodal approach to the medium allowed Packard to discuss potential parallels between two distinct (but not necessarily divergent) traditions of popular sequential art. Framing his analysis in two-parts, Packard discussed first the aesthetic and semiotic characteristics of comics, highlighting the formal characteristics that have been used in attempts at definition: among them, cartoonization and caricature, sequence and anatomy of the page, and the juxtaposition of script and image. In the second part, meanwhile, Packard turned to the question of popularity and comics as a tool for mass communication — a topic with particular relevance in the Chinese context of revolutionary socialism — before concluding with a discussion of the division of labor in comics-making, and the persistent association of popular sequential art with Rancière’s ‘representative regime’ in contrast with the ‘aesthetic regime’ of high art.</p>

<p>In the lively discussion that followed, participants raised a number of points with Packard, but perhaps most of all acknowledging that lianhuanhua, while sharing many points of similarity with comics as they are understood in the field of comics studies (being primarily composed of American and European comics strips and comic books, with a small carve out for Japanese manga) also remain distinct from this area of cultural production. A key example was the case of the so-called ‘Comics Code’, implemented in the 1950s to head off the threat of censorship from Congress. While lianhuanhua experienced a similar moral panic in the early 1950s following the victory of the Chinese Communist Party in the Civil War (1945–49), the extent to which the government was able to dramatically intervene in the production and consumption of lianhuanhua during this period far exceeded that of their contemporaries in the US. Such examples demonstrate just one of the many areas where not only historically informed but also critically engaged analysis like Packard’s can help contextualize lianhuanhua within the larger field of comics studies.</p>

<p>Appropriately, then, on the second day of the workshop, <a href="https://chinacomx.github.io/team/astrid/">Astrid Y. Xiao</a> got things started with her paper ‘Depoliticization, or Not: Role Model, Propaganda, and Lei Feng Comics,’ a close reading of lianhuanhua depicting the model soldier Lei Feng, drawing on examples from the 1960s and up to the present. Xiao argued that while it may be tempting to see such texts as becoming increasingly depoliticized, in fact a closer analysis reveals that, while not being afforded the same cultural significance as before, lianhuanhua featuring Lei Feng remain a potent site of not only political indoctrination, but also moral instruction. Turning to the 1980s, meanwhile, <a href="https://iao.cnrs.fr/laboratoire/membres/doctorants/norbert-danysz/">Norbert Danysz</a> presented his paper ‘Appropriations of Sergio Toppi and Stylistic Construction in 1980s Chinese Comics,’ highlighting the curious popularity of an Italian comics artist in China at this time. Providing numerous examples of ‘visual quotes’ from Toppi’s work in lianhuanhua at this time, Danysz argued that not only does the practice resemble the long-standing tradition of ‘swiping’ in comics, but further that elements of Toppi’s style (in particular the copious use of white space in his compositions) can be seen to be prefigured in the work of artists such as Fan Shengfu and Hua Shanchuan from the 1960s.</p>

<p>In her discussion of the two papers, <a href="https://biography.omicsonline.org/germany/heidelberg-university/petra-thiel-712848">Petra Thiel</a> raised the question of models (Toppi on the one hand, Lei Feng on the other) and underlined the importance of taking into account historical specifics, noting parallels between depictions of childhood and national development that tie together the themes explored by the respective presenters.</p>

<p>In the final panel for the workshop, <a href="https://chinacomx.github.io/team/jiu/">Jiu Song</a> presented her paper ‘Yesterday Once More: Reconnections of Lianhuanhua Memory Among Readers in the PRC,’ in which she discussed the initial results of her fieldwork in China, where she has been interviewing readers and fans of the medium, accessing relevant archives, and consulting oral histories produced by publishers. She highlighted the central challenge of this comparative work as finding agreement between individual memory and official narratives and balancing official accounts with grassroots ones. Last but not least, <a href="https://www.oaw.ruhr-uni-bochum.de/gc/team/Andreas_Seifert.html.en">Andreas Seifert</a> provided a lively account of his early research into, and collecting of lianhuanhua, beginning with his first encounters with the medium in the 1990s, and culminating in his PhD dissertation, published in 2008 as the monograph <a href="https://www.amazon.de/Bildgeschichten-f%C3%BCr-Chinas-Massen-Comicproduktion/dp/3412202029">Bildgeschichten für Chinas Massen: Comic und Comicproduktion im 20. Jahrhundert</a>.</p>

<p>In her discussion of these two presentations, in addition to noting the symmetry between the two papers (one on readers more broadly, and one from a very particular reader), <a href="https://uni-tuebingen.de/fakultaeten/philosophische-fakultaet/fachbereiche/asien-orient-wissenschaften/sinologie/personen/chinese-language-literature-and-culture/jun-prof-dr-emily-graf/">Emily Graf</a> drew our attention to the fact that although Seifert has since left academia, this early work provides a solid foundation for the field, not least because his collection of over 3,000 lianhuanhua can now be found in the collection of the CATS Library at Heidelberg University, with digital scans being available to researchers around the world.</p>

<p>The conference organizers accordingly invited participants to consult a selection of titles from exactly that collection, extending the theoretical discussions of the previous two days to a practical exercise in close reading. This provided a capstone to a workshop that touched on a range of topics and themes, all centered around the topic of lianhuanhua and Chinese comics more broadly. As Mandzunowski and Henningsen noted, the call for ‘lianhuanhua as method’ was meant in part as an academic provocation — a stimulus to challenge us to think more seriously about the ways that these texts can be used not just as illustrations of historical developments and political campaigns, but as objects of study in their own right. As the rich array of papers presented suggests, lianhuanhua represent an important and largely underappreciated area of cultural production, demonstrating both the continuity and discontinuity of China’s ‘long 20th century,’ and the challenges presented to researchers attempting to bring this body of texts into conversation with popular sequential art from other distinct cultural traditions.</p>

<p>While there is a lot more that can be said, I will end my summary here, to simply thank the organizers for a wonderful and stimulating workshop, inaugurating the exciting new ChinaComx project at the Centre for Asian and Transculutural Studies, Institute of Chinese Studies, Heidelberg University.</p>

<p><em>*Nick Stember is a media historian and translator of Chinese literature and popular culture. His work focuses on the remediation of the past through historical fiction and graphic narrative, considering the combined impacts of public policy and technology on the material conditions for the production and consumption of art and commercial entertainment. See more of his work at <a href="https://www.nickstember.com/">www.nickstember.com</a></em></p>

<hr />]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[After a bit over a year since the ChinaComx project commenced, and just over half a year after the team was assembled and our daily work on all things lianhuanhua began, we welcomed to Heidelberg 18 scholars of Chinese (and Asian) cartoon, caricature, comics, lianhuanhua, and other related forms of pictorial narratives for an intensively productive albeit fun workshop on 24-26 April 2025.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/LhhAsMethod2025.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/LhhAsMethod2025.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Damian Mandzunowski to Present at the Sonic Histories of East Asia Conference, 15-16 May in Venice</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/05/10/DamianVenice.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Damian Mandzunowski to Present at the Sonic Histories of East Asia Conference, 15-16 May in Venice" /><published>2025-05-10T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-05-10T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/05/10/DamianVenice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/05/10/DamianVenice.html"><![CDATA[<p>ChinaComx postdoc researcher <a href="https://chinacomx.github.io/team/damian/">Damian Mandzunowski</a> is to take part in the conference “Sonic Histories of East Asia: Thinking History Through Sound” held on 15-16 May 2025 at the <a href="https://www.unive.it/pag/28322/">Department of Asian and North African Studies at the Ca’ Foscari University of Venice</a>.</p>

<p>The conference, arising from a growing reception of the sonic turn also in Chinese and Asian Studies, explores how sound, voice, noise, radio, and other auditory media and modes can contribute to a field of Sound Studies that remains dominated by theories drawn from Western experience.</p>

<p>Damian will be presenting a chapter draft from his current book project on political study and other collective reading practices in the PRC. The paper, titled “Radio Study and the Sounds of Collective Reading Practices in the People’s Republic of China”, focuses, in the first part, on the phenomenon of radio study (<em>guangbo xuexi</em>) of the 1950s-1980s, and, in the second part, on various diegetic and nondiegetic sounds of collective reading activites.</p>

<p>Click <a href="assets/images/SonicHistoriesEastAsia2025.pdf" download="">here</a> for the program, and read more about Damian’s paper in his abstract:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Collective reading practices were a defining feature in Chinese state-socialist propaganda efforts after 1949. Occurring via obligatory political study classes for workers, cadres, soldiers, and others, these social rituals involved session leaders conducting and collective readers engaging in guided group study and text discussion. But, to take part in any such collective reading session was inevitably linked to the act of (collective) listening. Leaders often read selected fragments aloud and offered insights through brief lectures, expecting the collective readers to listen attentively to their voice and presented contents. At times, the collective readers heard without listening: the communicated contents passed through the minds of the listeners without retention. Radio broadcasts and other auditory media were also used, especially in rural areas, extending political education and disseminating information and
linking the auditory experience of politics with daily life. But these could break or malfunction, distorting the broadcast beyond comprehension. As recent scholarship has deepened our understanding of sound’s political uses (Lei 2019; Li 2020; Tang 2020; Santacaterina 2021; Wang 2022; Lekner 2022, 2024), this paper asks: In what ways did sound and voice work toward (or against) the goals pursued by organized forms of political study in the People’s Republic of China? In what ways did listening to Marx being read aloud differ from silent study of Marx? How did the voice, timbre, and enunciation of reading group leaders impact listeners’ reception of Lenin? How, then, did the party-state prepare for and evaluate the auditory elements of collective reading? This paper presents a comprehensive study of radio study (guangbo xuexi 广播学习) and similar sound-based study methods, utilizing archival broadcasts, radio magazines, state archives, and memoirs. In examining the auditory ways of collective reading practices, it explores the uses and failures of political communication under state socialism.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[ChinaComx postdoc researcher Damian Mandzunowski is to take part in the conference “Sonic Histories of East Asia: Thinking History Through Sound” held on 15-16 May 2025 at the Department of Asian and North African Studies at the Ca’ Foscari University of Venice.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/SonicHistoriesEastAsia2025.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/SonicHistoriesEastAsia2025.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">ChinaComx Workshop Announcement: Lianhuanhua as Method, Heidelberg 24-26 April 2025</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/04/10/LianhuanhuaAsMethod.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ChinaComx Workshop Announcement: Lianhuanhua as Method, Heidelberg 24-26 April 2025" /><published>2025-04-10T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-04-10T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/04/10/LianhuanhuaAsMethod</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/04/10/LianhuanhuaAsMethod.html"><![CDATA[<p>To kickstart the second year of our research project, the ChinaComx team cordially invites scholars working in Europe on Chinese comics, cartoons, picture stories, and other visual narratives to participate in the three-day workshop under the theme of “Lianhuanhua as Method”!</p>

<p>Workshop abstract:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>What does it mean to position a distinct medium as the defining element of inquiry? How does this change when the medium is also recognized as a specific (literary) genre? And how do approaches to studying history, art, culture, politics, and society shift when said medium / genre takes center stage in research? The medium in question is lianhuanhua, a distinct Chinese form of comics, and with this workshop, hosted by the ERC-ChinaComx project at Heidelberg University, we welcome interdisciplinary contributions examining lianhuanhua from diverse perspectives: whether as a distinct historical phenomenon, a part of global visual narratives, or a case study illuminating broader cultural or political contexts. How do we define lianhuanhua and how do our definitions change across different times and contexts? And what are the implications—direct and indirect—of approaching lianhuanhua as a research method? A central premise is that lianhuanhua serves as lens for (critical) inquiry: placing lianhuanhua at the forefront of analysis thus aims to expand all our various research approaches and fields. By starting with the image-text and then extending the analysis to other texts, events, and media in the larger context of production, dissemination, and consumption of lianhuanhua, the workshop seeks to offer a site for discussing how we understand the intersections of political communication, visual narratives, and meaning production.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We are looking forward to hearing two keynote lectures, by <a href="https://www.zo.uni-heidelberg.de/sinologie/institute/staff/mittler/">Barbara Mittler</a> and by <a href="https://mekuwi.phil-fak.uni-koeln.de/personen/professor-innen/prof-dr-stephan-packard">Stephan Packard</a>, as well as to offering a hands-on comics browsing and rummaging session—in addition to featuring over a dozen fascinating paper presentations and the ensuing discussions.</p>

<p>Join the workshop on <strong>Thursday, Friday, and Saturday 24-26 April 2025 at CATS Heidelberg</strong>.</p>

<p>Click <a href="/assets/images/2025-ChinaComxWorkshop-LianhuanhuaAsMethod_ProgramPublic.pdf" download="">here</a> for the full workshop program in PDF, and <a href="mailto:chinacomx.erc@gmail.com">send us an email</a> to register for participation. We look forward to welcoming you to Heidelberg soon!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[To kickstart the second year of our research project, the ChinaComx team cordially invites scholars working in Europe on Chinese comics, cartoons, picture stories, and other visual narratives to participate in the three-day workshop under the theme of “Lianhuanhua as Method”!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2025-ChinaComxWorkshop-LianhuanhuaAsMethod_Poster.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/2025-ChinaComxWorkshop-LianhuanhuaAsMethod_Poster.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Astrid Y. Xiao to Present at The Child and the Book Conference 2025 in Tilburg</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/04/05/AstridTilburg.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Astrid Y. Xiao to Present at The Child and the Book Conference 2025 in Tilburg" /><published>2025-04-05T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-04-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/04/05/AstridTilburg</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/04/05/AstridTilburg.html"><![CDATA[<p>ChinaComx Phd Candidate <a href="https://chinacomx.github.io/team/astrid/">Astrid Y. Xiao</a> will present her research during the 2025 <a href="https://www.diggitmagazine.com/events/child-and-book-conference-2025">Child and the Book Conference</a>. This year’s edition is running under the theme “Children Shaping The(ir) World: Between the Exceptional and the Everyday” and will be hosted on 23-25 April 2025 at <a href="https://www.tilburguniversity.edu/current/events/child-book-2025">Tilburg University</a>, Netherlands.</p>

<p>Astrid will present her paper in Session 2 (14:00–15:45) as part of Panel 4: Political Childhoods, chaired by <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Anna-Czernow">Anna Czernow</a>. Titled “Inventing A Non-typical Young Role Model in Communist China: Everyday Heroism in Comics about Lei Feng (1960s–2020s)”, her talk explores how children’s comics and picturebooks in China has shaped political and moral ideals across generations, through the evolving portrayal of the national icon Lei Feng.</p>

<p>Astrid’s paper abstract:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Considering the powerful influence of role models on youth, crafting and promoting role models is (and was) a common strategy for nation-building and educating younger generations in China. These role models are often titled “(Little) Heroes”, with their faces and stories being frequently featured in textbooks, school wall newspapers, and on children’s bookshelves. In 1960s communist China, these celebrated heroes primarily displayed traits of loyalty to Chairman Mao and the Chinese Communist Party, patriotism, and a strong passion for revolution and socialist construction. While heroism is a broad concept that also includes acts of kindness and courage in everyday life—acknowledged today as the “banality of heroism” (Franco and Zimbardo, 2006)—in the 1960s, China predominantly favored the celebration of exceptional heroes in its political and educational narratives. This paper focuses on an exception of the exceptional. Lei Feng, a real-life People’s Liberation Army soldier who died aged 22 in 1962, was known as a moral exemplar for his pure altruism and numerous good deeds. Since the 1960s, Lei Feng’s stories from his childhood, adolescence, and young adulthood have been crafted into various forms of propagandist materials (story collections, posters, comics, etc.) and have been widely received by Chinese children from different generations. By close reading 14 comics and picturebooks about Lei Feng produced between the 1960s and 2020s, I argue that, from the very beginning, these visual texts oscillated between the grand narratives of national construction and a mundane hero who does every small everyday deed well. This oscillation tries to break free from the inappropriateness of conventional exceptional hero narratives in Lei Feng’s case. Ultimately, over more than half a century of oscillation, everyday heroism has clearly triumphed. Whether in terms of characterization or artistic style, 21st-century comics depict Lei Feng as more commonplace and accessible, bringing him closer to his young friends and followers both in the comics and in real life. The victory of everyday heroism in the comics about Lei Feng can not only be seen as a shift in the styles of political propaganda in modern China, but it also demonstrates that, over the past decades, child readers have been rediscovered and reevaluated.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Download the full conference program <a href="https://www.diggitmagazine.com/sites/default/files/2025-04/CBC25_Programme.pdf">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[ChinaComx Phd Candidate Astrid Y. Xiao will present her research during the 2025 Child and the Book Conference. This year’s edition is running under the theme “Children Shaping The(ir) World: Between the Exceptional and the Everyday” and will be hosted on 23-25 April 2025 at Tilburg University, Netherlands.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/TheChildAndTheBookConferenceTilburg.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/TheChildAndTheBookConferenceTilburg.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Lena Henningsen to Take Part in Roundtable Discussion on the Art of Copying at AAS 2025</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/03/10/LenaAASRoundtable.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lena Henningsen to Take Part in Roundtable Discussion on the Art of Copying at AAS 2025" /><published>2025-03-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-03-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/03/10/LenaAASRoundtable</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/03/10/LenaAASRoundtable.html"><![CDATA[<p>Our PI, <a href="https://chinacomx.github.io/team/lena/">Lena Henningsen</a>, will take part in a <a href="https://asianstudies.confex.com/asianstudies/2025/meetingapp.cgi/Session/8453">roundtable session</a> during this years’ AAS annual conference in Columbus, Ohio.</p>

<p>Titled “On Copying: An Interdisciplinary Conversation”, the roundtable brings together <a href="http://ealac.columbia.edu/eugenia-lean/">Eugenia Lean, Columbia University</a>; <a href="https://vcresearch.berkeley.edu/faculty/winnie-wong">Winnie Wong, University of California, Berkeley</a>; <a href="https://www.zo.uni-heidelberg.de/sinologie/institute/staff/henningsen/">Lena Henningsen, Heidelberg University</a>; <a href="https://earlymodernworld.brown.edu/people/kaijun-chen">Kaijun Chen, Brown University</a>; and <a href="https://www.concordia.ca/faculty/yuan-yi.html">Yuan Yi, Concordia University</a>; and is to be chaired by <a href="https://history.uchicago.edu/directory/Jacob-Eyferth">Jacob Eyferth, University of Chicago</a>.</p>

<p>Join the conversation on <strong>Friday, March 14, during the 9:00 AM–10:30 AM session at Hyatt, Fayette, 2nd Floor (Panel 2-018)</strong>!</p>

<p>Abstract:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>The practice of copying, broadly defined, has drawn scholarly interests from an array of disciplines in the China field as China emerges as a powerful economy while at the same time achieving notoriety as the “quintessential copycat.” Instead of holding onto its conventional definition, mostly informed by the contemporary IPR regime, recent scholars have problematized the notion of copying itself by historicizing its varying practices in different fields. STS scholars recast copying (or tinkering or prototyping) as a serious technological endeavor with emphasis on its experimental nature; art historians redefine imitation as transformative artistic work; and literary scholars approach hand-copying as a way of rewriting where the boundary between authors and readers remains fluid. Some historians, on the other hand, challenge the assumption about the lenient attitude toward copying in Chinese culture while others question the entrenched link between China and copying by demonstrating that it was not a uniquely Chinese practice. All these studies call for a more nuanced approach to the history of copying in China and beyond with attention to its temporal changes in different social and cultural contexts. This roundtable session presents discussants who have addressed these issues in their respective fields, providing an interdisciplinary forum to discuss this highly contested (and often politically charged) subject.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Click <a href="assets/images/AAS-AC-2025-Complete-Online-PDF-1.pdf">here</a> for the conference program in PDF, or head over to the <a href="https://www.asianstudies.org/conference/">conference’s website</a> for more information.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our PI, Lena Henningsen, will take part in a roundtable session during this years’ AAS annual conference in Columbus, Ohio.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/AAS2025.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/AAS2025.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>